Guide to the Agnes De Lima Collection of Alyse Gregory
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Agnes de Lima collection of Alyse Gregory
1924-1968
1939-1967
YCAL MSS 164
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.14
(7 boxes)
The collection consists chiefly of letters from Gregory to de Lima, concerning their friendship; Gregory's writing and her life in Dorset and Devon; her interest in the New School for Social Research; and Randolph Silliman Bourne, Sigrid de Lima, the Powys family, and other literary friends. Other letters include correspondence between Gregory and Sigrid de Lima and Elizabeth Shepley Sergeant, and letters to Agnes de Lima from literary friends and publishers concerning Llewelyn Powys's letters and writings. Also present are essays by Gregory and Powys, and clippings, photographs, and other papers relating to Gregory and her friendship with de Lima.
De Lima, Agnes
Gregory, Alyse, 1884-1967
Powys, Llewelyn, 1884-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Agnes de Lima, 1966 and 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7: Restricted until 2030. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 6: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
AGNES DE LIMA (1887-1974) AND ALYSE GREGORY (1884-1967)
Agnes de Lima, educator and author, served as public relations director for the New School for Social Research, 1940-1960. She began a close friendship with Alyse Gregory in 1915, which continued until Gregory's death in 1967. Gregory was godmother to de Lima's daughter, author Sigrid de Lima (1921-1999). Agnes de Lima assisted in collecting letters of Gregory's husband Llewelyn Powys for publication by John Lane in 1943, and she acted as a literary agent in the United States for Powys's later works. A full biographical note for Alyse Gregory is provided in the register for the Alyse Gregory Papers (YCAL MSS 163).
Scope and Contents
The Agnes de Lima Collection of Alyse Gregory consists of letters from Gregory to de Lima, correspondence of Gregory and de Lima with others, and writings, clippings, photographs, and other papers relating to Gregory, her friendship with de Lima, and de Lima's interest in writings of Gregory and Llewelyn Powys.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: Agnes de Lima Correspondence and Alyse Gregory Correspondence. Agnes de Lima Correspondence consists chiefly of letters from Gregory to de Lima. Letters concern their friendship and Gregory's writing, particularly her autobiography The Day is Gone and her biography of Randolph Bourne; de Lima's memories of Bourne; and Gregory's efforts to collect letters of Llewelyn Powys. Also discussed are the education and career of Sigrid de Lima; Gregory's interest in the New School for Social Research; Gregory's life in Dorset during and after the Second World War and her later life in Devon; and Gregory's friendships with members of the Powys family and other writers. Some letters are annotated by de Lima concerning their content. Other correspondence consists of letters to de Lima, with some outgoing carbons, concerning Powys's letters and publication of his later works, including Love and Death, A Baker's Dozen, and Swiss Essays. Some transcripts of related letters from Gregory and Powys to publishers and friends are also present. Alyse Gregory Correspondence includes letters to and from Gregory, with concentrations of letters from Gregory to Sigrid de Lima and from Elizabeth Shepley Sergeant to Gregory.
Series II, Other Papers, is organized into four subseries. Essays by Alyse Gregory consists of drafts of several essays sent by Gregory to de Lima. Writings of Others includes drafts from Llewelyn Powys's Swiss Essays, brief notes concerning his Love and Death, and a biographical essay about Powys, written by Louis Marlow. Clippings and Other Printed Material, arranged alphabetically by subject, includes materials by and about several members of the Powys family and other friends of Gregory, most sent by Gregory to de Lima. Photographs includes images of Llewelyn Powys's death mask and Gregory's home in Devon.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; English literature -- 20th Century; Women authors, American -- 20th Century; Devon (England) -- Social life and customs; Dorset (England) -- Social life and customs; Bourne, Randolph Silliman, 1886-1918; De Lima, Agnes; De Lima, Sigrid, 1921-1999; Gregory, Alyse, 1884-1967; Powys, Llewelyn, 1884-1939; Sergeant, Elizabeth Shepley, 1881-1965; Powys family; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997)
- Correspondence, 1924-1968; Series I; 1.47; (4 boxes)
  - AGNES DE LIMA CORRESPONDENCE
    - Abbott, Claude Colleer, 1950 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Artinian, Artine (LP transcript), 1938 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1941 Feb-Mar (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Blum, Frances, 1940 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Blum, Frances (LP transcript), 1939 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bye, George (AG transcript), 1940 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Byington, Jean L. Gregory, 1966 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Colum, Padraic, 1940 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - De Casseres, Benjamin, 1940 Mar (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Decision, 1941 Apr (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - de Lima, Agnes, 1932-41 (Box 1, Folder 11-18)
    - de Lima, Agnes, 1942-45 (Box 1, Folder 19-25)
    - de Lima, Agnes, 1947-50 (Box 2, Folder 26-34)
    - de Lima, Agnes, 1951-61 (Box 2, Folder 35-41)
    - de Lima, Agnes, 1962-67, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42-51)
    - de Lima, Sigrid (LP transcript), 1939 Sep 8 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Dreiser, Helen Patges, 1941 Mar-Apr (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Dreiser, Helen Patges (LP transcript), 1936, [1939?] (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - English, Herbert (LP transcript), 1935 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Fararr, John, 1940 Apr-Sep (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Farrar, John (AG transcript), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Farrar & Rinehart
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Farrar, John, Box 3, folders 56-57
    - Feipel, Louis Nicholas, 1940 Mar (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Feipel, Louis Nicholas (LP transcripts), 1924-39 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Greenwood, C. J.
      See: John Lane Company, Box 3, folder 64
    - Hardy, Evelyn, 1967 Oct 13 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Harper's Magazine, 1957 Mar 18 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1940 Apr 27 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Howe, Quincy
      See: Simon and Schuster, inc., Box 3, folders 76-77
    - Hoyt, Mrs. (LP transcript) (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - John Lane Company (AG transcripts), 1941 Jun (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Johnson, Arthur (LP transcripts), 1926 Jul-Nov (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Lee, Lawrence
      See: Virginia Quarterly Review, Box 3, folder 82
    - Loveman, Amy
      See: Saturday Review of Literature, Box 3, folder 72
    - Mann, Klaus
      See: Decision, Box 2, folder 10
    - Manning, Rosemary, 1968 Apr 26 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Marsh, Felicia (to LP), n.y. Oct 16 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Meyer, Catharine
      See: Harper's Magazine, Box 3, folder 61
    - New Directions, 1940 Jan 14 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Penny, Lucy Powys, 1961, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Powys, Marian, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Powys, Philippa, 1958, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Saturday Review of Literature, 1940 Mar 15 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Scott-Maxwell, Florida, 1958, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Sergeant, Elizabeth Shepley, 1940 Jul-Aug (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Shimkin, Leon
    - Siberell, Lloyd Emerson, 1940-41, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Simon and Schuster, inc., 1940-48 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Simon and Schuster, inc. (AG transcript), 1941 Feb 14 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Starkie, Enid, 1959 Aug 12 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Townsend, Myron, 1940, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Untermeyer, Jean Starr (AG transcripts), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Van Doren, Irita Taylor (LP transcripts), 1925-29 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Virginia Quarterly Review, 1940 Jun (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Warren, Dale
      See: Houghton Mifflin Company, Box 3, folder 62
    - Weeks, Edward
      See: Atlantic Monthly, Box 1, folder 3
  - ALYSE GREGORY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Brooks, Gladys, 1952 Jan 24 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Byington, Jean L. Gregory, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - de Lima, Sigrid, 1943-53, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Hopkins, Kenneth
      See: de Lima, Agnes, Box 2, folder 40
    - Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1948 Mar 24 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Marlowe, Dave
      See: de Lima, Agnes, Box 2, folder 28
    - Sergeant, Elizabeth Shepley, 1940-57, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 87-91)
    - Siberell, Lloyd Emerson, 1940 Jan 16 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Wescott, Glenway, 1940 Mar 5 (Box 4, Folder 93)
      Scope and Contents
      Envelope only
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 94)
      See also: de Lima, Agnes, Box 3, folder 48
- Other Papers, 1938-1961; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  - ESSAYS BY ALYSE GREGORY
    - "Cyrus Woodward" (title page only), typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "Reflections of an Expatriate," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - "Samuel Taylor Coleridge," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - "Six Deaths in the Afternoon," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - WRITINGS BY OTHERS
    - Marlow, Louis. "Llewelyn Powys," (essay), typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Powys, Llewelyn. "Corrections to be Made in Love and Death, typescript (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Powys, Lleweyn. Drafts from Swiss Essays, typescript (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified. List of "qualities which should be possessed by a writer of fiction", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - CLIPPINGS AND OTHER PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Costigan, Giovanni, 1961 Jan-Feb (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - de Lima, Agnes (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Gregory, Alyse, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - King-Hall, Stephen, 1941-46, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Lucas, Hester, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1941-57 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Powys, Littleton, 1955 Sep (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Powys, Llewelyn, 1938-47, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Powys, Theodore Francis, 1953 Dec 4 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - World War, 1939-1945, 1941-47, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Other clippings and printed material, 1947-61. n.d. (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Photograph of Durdle Door, Dorset, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Photograph of Llewelyn Powys's death mask (2 copies), 1939 Nov? (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Photographs of Velthams Cottage, near Tiverton, Devon (Box 5, Folder 116)
- Restricted Fragile Oversize, 1.25; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 4 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Box 1, folder 24 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Box 2, folder 37 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Box 2, folder 38 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Box 3, folder 53 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Box 3, folder 54 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Box 3, folder 68 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Box 3, folder 76 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Box 3, folder 82 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Box 4, folder 85 (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Box 5, folder 100 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Box 5, folder 102 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Box 5, folder 105 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Box 5, folder 106 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Box 5, folder 107 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Box 5, folder 108 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Box 5, folder 109 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Box 5, folder 110 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Box 5, folder 111 (Box 6, Folder 135)
- Restricted Papers, 0.2; (1 box)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Agnes de Lima, 1968
  Restricted until 2030. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Restricted letters from AG to Agnes de Lima (Box 7, Folder 136)